<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>techniques on Retrolog.io</title>
    <link>https://retrolog.io/tags/techniques/</link>
    <description>Recent content in techniques on Retrolog.io</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 28 Mar 2020 17:26:26 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://retrolog.io/tags/techniques/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The COVID-19 Retrospective</title>
      <link>https://retrolog.io/blog/the-covid-19-retrospective/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Mar 2020 17:26:26 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://retrolog.io/blog/the-covid-19-retrospective/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://retrolog.io/images/the-covid-19-retrospective.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an attempt to lighten the mood a bit during this difficult times, I put together a new retrospective technique inspired by the latest development on COVID-19 and what we know about how to fight it. Keep reading if you want to know more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like in previous posts, I use &lt;a href=&#34;https://miro.com&#34;&gt;miro&lt;/a&gt; as a virtual whiteboard. This is now more important than ever given the lockdown restrictions in most countries around the world, so chances are that your team is working fully remotely at the minute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;prepare-the-stage&#34;&gt;Prepare the stage&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Divide the board in 6 sections like in the image below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://retrolog.io/images/the-covid-19-retrospective-2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider adding an ice-breaker as well to warm things up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;gather-data-10-min&#34;&gt;Gather data (10 min)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Give participants 7 minutes to write down their thoughts on virtual post-it notes in the five sections allocated for it. The 6th one is just for the facilitator to take notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are our biggest challenges?&lt;/strong&gt; Like with Coronavirus, teams face difficult challenges that need to be explicitely called out and discussed to ensure alignment and enable continuous improvement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are our main pain points?&lt;/strong&gt; Like staying at home for a few weeks to fight a virus that spreads easily, teams suffer from technical debt, processes that require more than they should or organisational issues that get in the way. Use this section to write down all those things that are keeping you awake at night. Note that this section differs from the one above in that challenges are things we need to achieve in order to move forward, whereas pain points are typically a consequence of past decisions or contextual circumstances, but based on things that have happened already.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What quick wins will make us succeed?&lt;/strong&gt; Small things like washing your hands can have a huge impact if done right. Think of all the short term things you can do now that will take you closer to your long term goals further down the line. Focus on low hanging fruits here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What will make us succeed in the long run?&lt;/strong&gt; For what we know, even at record breaking speed, a vaccine for Coronavirus is not likely to be available for at least another 18 months. Yet, we need to start working on it now because it&#39;s the right thing to do and it will had the biggest long term impact. Similarly, what things does your team need to start working on now that will pay off in a few months.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What should we avoid?&lt;/strong&gt; At the moment, you should only travel if your journey is absolutely essential. Anything else will mean you are increasing the risk of spreading the virus and affecting key workers like healthcare professionals, that are trying to get to their workplaces. Similarly, what things does your team need to avoid as you move forward? These are not pain points from the past, and not necessarily challenges that you know you&#39;ll have to overcome, but rather things that you know already will get in the way if they materialise. Include here risks that you are aware of.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;generate-insights-30-min&#34;&gt;Generate insights (30 min)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s time to brainstorm and generate lots of ideas, but in the interest of time, filter first so that you can focus on the most relevant ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go through the notes and cluster similar topics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Give participants 5 votes each and set a 3 minute timer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start discussing from the most voted idea.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ask questions to trigger conversations if they don&#39;t flow naturally e.g. why did you vote this note? what did you mean by X when you wrote it down? Is this related to a particular event that happened recently? How have you seen this apply in previous experiences? If you had unlimited resources, how would you tackle it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;decide-what-to-do-10-min&#34;&gt;Decide what to do (10 min)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For each discussion, make sure that you identify potential actions for the team to work on in the next iteration. &lt;strong&gt;Each action must have an owner&lt;/strong&gt;. You can do this as you generate insights in the previous step, no need to wait.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use some time at the end to ask people to sign up for the unassigned actions, and wrap things up by summarising the main points that were discussed as well as the final set of outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope this is helpful. Take care, stay safe and until next time 👋&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Saint Patrick&#39;s Day Inspired Retrospective</title>
      <link>https://retrolog.io/blog/a-saint-patricks-day-inspired-retrospective/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Mar 2020 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://retrolog.io/blog/a-saint-patricks-day-inspired-retrospective/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://retrolog.io/images/a-saint-patricks-themed-retrospective.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saint Patrick&#39;s Day is around the corner. The 17th of March is celebrated in green and gold all around the world. I thought it might be fun to design a retrospective based on this festivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use &lt;a href=&#34;https://miro.com&#34;&gt;miro&lt;/a&gt; as a virtual whiteboard. It&#39;s a visual collaboration tool that makes it very easy for remote teams to share and organise ideas. Perfect for retrospectives!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this is not your first retrospective, take 5 minutes to review actions for previous ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-layout&#34;&gt;The layout&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Divide the board in three sections like in the image below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://retrolog.io/images/a-saint-patricks-themed-retrospective-2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Trinity and the Shamrock&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first legend of Saint Patrick says he used a shamrock to explain the Holy Trinity to the Irish back in the 5th century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s use that analogy to discuss three fundamental areas that need to be considered by high performing teams, Technology, Processes and People.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Technology: which technologies are we using at the moment that help us achieve our goals? which tools and patterns?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Process: which processes help us be efficient and keep us on our toes?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People: take a moment to shout out any remarkable things your team mates did during the last iteration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Give participants 5 minutes to write down as many notes as they can in each of the categories.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Review notes and cluster similar topics to simplify the discussion later.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Banishing all the Snakes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second legend of Saint Patrick says he banished all the snakes from the island, chasing them into the sea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this section participants should focus on all the things that are affecting team performance and should be &amp;ldquo;bannished into the sea&amp;rdquo;. Feel free to focus on similar areas than the ones above i.e. Technology, Process and People, but do not limit the list to those. For example, you might want to include incidents or events that happened in the last iteration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Give participants 5 minutes to write down as many notes as they can in each of the categories.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Review notes and cluster similar topics to simplify the discussion later.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Walking Stick grows into a Tree&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third legend of Saint Patrick says he thrust his walking stick into the ground wherever he was evangelising, and at the place now known as Aspatria (ash of Patrick), the message of the dogma took so long to get through to the people there that the stick had taken root by the time he was ready to move on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will use this last section to capture actions that will help the team take root and grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Voting and discussion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Run a poll to identify the most relevant clusters. Discuss focusing on two aspects:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Situation: what&#39;s the reason behind the notes? what is the context?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Action: what can we do to leverage a strength even more or mitigate a recurring issue? How can we improve our tools and processes?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;End the meeting by making sure each action has an owner. And if it&#39;s the end of the day, maybe go to the pub and grab a traditional Irish beverage. Cheers! 🍻&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mastering Pair Programming in 5 Minutes</title>
      <link>https://retrolog.io/blog/mastering-pair-programming-in-5-minutes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Mar 2020 16:41:21 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://retrolog.io/blog/mastering-pair-programming-in-5-minutes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://retrolog.io/images/mastering-pair-programming-in-5-minutes.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is heavily based on &lt;a href=&#34;https://martinfowler.com/articles/on-pair-programming.html&#34;&gt;https://martinfowler.com/articles/on-pair-programming.html&lt;/a&gt; (38 min read). That is, however, a very long (yet very good) article. For those of us that can&#39;t or don&#39;t want to afford spending that long, I collated its main points and added a few twists of my own. I hope it&#39;s useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;why-bother&#34;&gt;Why bother?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to some studies e.g. &lt;a href=&#34;https://collaboration.csc.ncsu.edu/laurie/Papers/XPSardinia.PDF,&#34;&gt;https://collaboration.csc.ncsu.edu/laurie/Papers/XPSardinia.PDF,&lt;/a&gt; some of the most significant benefits of pair programming are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many mistakes get caught as they are being typed in rather than in QA test or in the field (continuous code reviews)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The end defect content is statistically lower (continuous code reviews)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The designs are better and code length shorter (ongoing brainstorming and pair relaying)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The team solves problems faster (pair relaying)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People learn significantly more, about the system and about software development (line-of-sight learning)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The project ends up with multiple people understanding each piece of the system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People learn to work together and talk more often together, giving better information flow and team dynamics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People enjoy their work more&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The development cost for these benefits is not the 100% that might be expected, but approximately 15%. This is repaid in shorter and less expensive testing, quality assurance, and field support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;how-to-pair&#34;&gt;How to pair&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the task involves coding, three options:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Driver and Navigator&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Driver is the person with the keyboard focused on completing the immediate goal at hand, temporarily ignoring larger issues. Should talk through what they are doing while doing it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Navigator is the observer while the driver types, reviews the code on-the-go, gives directions and shares thoughts. Keeps an eye on the larger issues, potential bugs and makes notes for next steps and obstacles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Driver thinks &lt;strong&gt;tactically&lt;/strong&gt; and is detail-oriented while the Navigator thinks &lt;strong&gt;strategically&lt;/strong&gt; and has the bigger picture in mind.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tips:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start with a reasonably well-defined task&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Agree on one tiny goal at a time e.g. defined by a unit test or a commit message&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Switch roles regularly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As Navigator, avoid tactical thinking, you&#39;ll be tempted! Make notes on potential obstacles and ideas and discuss after the tiny goal is done, so the Driver can stay in the flow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ping Pong&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TDD&lt;/strong&gt; oriented&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ping - Person A writes a failing test&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pong - Person B writes the implementation to make the test pass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ping - Person B writes a failing test&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pong - Person A writes the implementation to make the test pass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tips:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start with a clearly defined task&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each Pong can be followed by a code refactoring step done together by both (Red - Green - Refactor)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strong-Style&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For an idea to go from your head into the computer, it MUST go through someone else&#39;s hands&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Particularly useful for &lt;strong&gt;knowledge transfer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Driver is a novice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Navigator is much more experienced with the task at hand&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Participants &lt;strong&gt;do not switch positions&lt;/strong&gt; throughout the session&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tips:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Driver totally trusts the Navigator and should be comfortable with incomplete understanding&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Why&amp;rdquo; questions and challenging the solution should be discussed after the implementation session&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&#39;t overuse this technique&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Great for initial knowledge transfer but the goal is to transition to the other styles after a while&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the task does not involve coding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Planning&lt;/strong&gt; - what&#39;s our goal?
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;E.g. pairing on Epic Ownership or aspects that overlap multiple epics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand the problem, read through the story and play back to each other how you understand it to make sure there is alignment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clear up any questions or potential misunderstandings with the Produc Owner / Engineering Manager / Epic Owner&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Double check your Definition of Ready to make sure you have everything to get started&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Brainstorm a potential solution, together or individually and then present ideas to each other. If one is more familiar with the domain or technology, take some time to share context.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plan your approach, list out the steps to get to the solution you chose and how you will test it. Write them down! so that we can track progress (e.g. in JIRA as subtasks)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spikes&lt;/strong&gt; - research and explore
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Define a list of questions that you need to answer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Split up, divide and conquer. Alternatively, try to find answers for the same questions separately.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Search your company&#39;s intranet and messaging system, and any other resources you can find&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read up on concepts that are new to both of you&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get back together after a previously agreed upon time-box, share and discuss&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Documentation&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reflect together if any documentation is necessary for what you&#39;ve done&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a document together. Alternatively, one person creates it, then the other reviews it and &amp;ldquo;wordsmiths&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pairing reduces the chance of skipping documentation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For time management you can use the pomodoro technique, small breaks after 25min and longer breaks after 2h.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pair rotations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&#39;t stay in the same pair for more than 2-3 days&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This avoids silos, increase collective code ownership, and favours more code review on-the-go&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It also keeps things fresh, particularly when you are working on something tedious and energy-draining&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The person who stays is called the Anchor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plan the day:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pairing requires a certain level of scheduling and calendar coordination&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start the day by agreeing on how many hours you are going to pair, and whether you need to plan around meetings or other commitments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If someone is off-sick or on leave, rotate the pair&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consider leaving some time at the beginning/end of the day for other activities e.g. checking your email or self-studying&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Physical setup:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure both have enough space, chairs included, clear up the desk if necessary&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Decide if you want to use one keyboard or two, same for the mouse. No hard rule, whatever works. Some other factors into play are hygiene and how much space is actually available.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consider using screen share on Zoom so that each one can use their own laptop&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Agree on a default the first time, so that you don&#39;t have to discuss this every time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remote pairing is ok as long as the internet connection is good enough, there is no background noise (use mute otherwise), and both of you agree to it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Celebrate when you have accomplished a task together, you earned it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things to avoid:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Drifting apart during the pairing session e.g. reading emails or using your phone. These can come across as disrespectful and distracts you from the task at hand. If you really need to check something, make it transparent, say what you are doing and why&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Micro-managing e.g. &amp;ldquo;Now type this&amp;hellip;&amp;quot;, &amp;ldquo;Now we need to create a class called&amp;hellip;&amp;quot;, &amp;ldquo;Press Cmd + Shift O&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Impatience, apply the 5-seconds-rule instead (when the Navigator sees something &amp;ldquo;wrong&amp;rdquo; and wants to comment, wait at least 5 seconds in case the driver already has it in mind, so that you don&#39;t interrupt their flow unnecessarily)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keyboard hogging, are you controlling the keyboard all the time? Sharing is caring ❤&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pairing 8 hours per day, it&#39;s not sustainable, it&#39;s too exhausting and in practice there are other things you need to do other than coding&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is not &amp;ldquo;THE&amp;rdquo; right way, try different approaches and find what works for you and your team.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>