<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>leadership on Retrolog.io</title>
    <link>https://retrolog.io/tags/leadership/</link>
    <description>Recent content in leadership on Retrolog.io</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 28 Jun 2020 17:30:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://retrolog.io/tags/leadership/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>A Pragmatic Approach to Roadmapping</title>
      <link>https://retrolog.io/blog/a-pragmatic-approach-to-roadmapping/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jun 2020 17:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://retrolog.io/blog/a-pragmatic-approach-to-roadmapping/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://retrolog.io/images/a-pragmatic-approach-to-roadmapping.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creating a roadmap can be a challenging task. I can&#39;t really say I am an expert on the matter, but have done it a couple of times. The most recent one, I put together a workshop that got fairly positive feedback and so I&#39;m sharing it for the benefit of anyone interested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post describes a pragmatic approach to creating a roadmap for half a year, but can be extrapolated to cover whatever time period you need. Just be aware that the longest the period, the fuzziest it will be after the first 6 months, particularly in an agile environment with quarterly OKRs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;1-plan-out-the-session&#34;&gt;1. Plan out the session&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used a Miro board as the canvas for the workshop. Having a tool that allows for realtime remote collaboration is essential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lay out the different steps (which I cover below) and add a time estimate, so that everyone can check if each part is overrunning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don&#39;t need to cover absolutely everything in one session. Do it if you can, but this can be quite challenging, as there is a lot to cover, and probably people will be tired after max two hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A high level overview of the board we used looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://retrolog.io/images/a-pragmatic-approach-to-roadmapping-1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;2-ice-breaker&#34;&gt;2. Ice-breaker&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s usually a good idea to start with an ice-breaker that will get people in the right mood. During the workshop, everyone needs to be participative. Spending a few minutes at the beginning, having a laugh and chatting informally, will definitely be beneficial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can use classic exercises from your retrospectives, like guessing everyone&#39;s favourite food or describing your current mood with an emoji. The sky is the limit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;3-set-out-expectations&#34;&gt;3. Set out expectations&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is worth spending 5-10 minutes clarifying the expectations for the workshop. What are we trying to achieve, what&#39;s in scope and what&#39;s not?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the facilitator, come prepared with a proposal. Read through it during the meeting and get agreement or make amendments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the categories we covered last time were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What we should do if we had unlimited time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What we are actually doing today&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What we are not doing today&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What we should follow up on&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are just examples, feel free to come up with your own version.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;4-build-individual-roadmaps&#34;&gt;4. Build individual roadmaps&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here you will start the actual roadmapping exercise. It has a few steps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;41-list-all-the-projects-you-can-think-of&#34;&gt;4.1. List all the projects you can think of&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a column, list all the projects/epics in your area. It doesn&#39;t matter if they have been discussed previously or not, and you are encouraged to think out-of-the-box.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a facilitator, it is a good idea to pre-populate the list with the projects you know of already. This will save time and will serve as an example for others to contribute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember you are listing projects, not tasks nor programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Give people time to add projects to the list. You can use different techniques for this e.g. round robin, silent brainstorming, 1-2-4-all, free for all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of this stage, you will have an unestimated, unordered and unowned list of projects that contains everything everyone in the room knows about the work you need to do in your area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;42-estimate-using-t-shirt-sizes&#34;&gt;4.2 Estimate using t-shirt sizes&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Estimates are context dependent. What is big for one team, might be medium for another. Here, use whatever makes more sense to your team/area. For example, if you always work on one single thing at a time vs you usually parallelise two or three things, your estimates might differ. These are just ballpark figures, so don&#39;t worry too much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sizes we used were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Small = 1/3 of the quarter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Medium = 2/3 of the quarter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Large = 1 quater&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Extra large = more than 1 quarter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Miro, it is easy to resize rectangles (projects) to match the reference sizes at the top of the list (see the template).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go through the projects from the top and estimate all of them. On a second pass, try to break down the biggest ones into smaller chunks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;43-order-projects-using-a-naive-approach&#34;&gt;4.3 Order projects using a naive approach&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A simple bubble-sort will do. Starting from the top decide wether the next project should be done before or after the previous one. Very quickly we started moving things up or down, and ended up with a reasonably well sorted list. Doesn&#39;t have to be perfect, but it should help to group things that need to be done roughly at the same time, and identify things that can probably wait.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;44-roughly-define-which-team-should-own-each-project&#34;&gt;4.4 Roughly define which team should own each project&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are building a roadmap for more than one team, at this point is useful to colour-code the projects to highlight which team will be the official owner of the project. In practice, this means the team that will provide an Epic Owner for the project. If you are unfamiliar with the concept of Epic Owner, it&#39;s the person in charge of an epic acting like the project manager (plus other things, but that&#39;s a topic for a different time).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes ownership is shared, and sometimes you just don&#39;t know. This is absolutely fine at this point, especially for things that will happen 2+ quarters away from now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;45-build-roadmaps-individually&#34;&gt;4.5 Build roadmaps individually&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Give people 10-15 minutes to build their own roadmaps with the projects on the list. The goal is to prioritise and parallelise things. Think about dependencies and respect the order as much as possible. But don&#39;t feel constrained by the order that came out of 4.3. It was ordered naively after all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;5-build-a-straw-man-roadmap-together&#34;&gt;5. Build a straw-man roadmap together&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, everyone should be pretty familiar with the items in the roadmap, the non-controversial topics, and the trickiest ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a group, try to put together a final version. Use arrows to explicitly flag dependencies between projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s very important to remember that this is just a straw-man roadmap, meaning it&#39;s an advanced draft. Not something to be publicly shared, as it needs more work still. But a helpful internal tool nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The output will be useful in deciding what to do next, and for OKR planning. But things can, and most certainly will, change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;6-reconcile-with-okrs&#34;&gt;6. Reconcile with OKRs&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s think for a minute about what we have. We have a list of things that we want to build as an area (area meaning the part of the business you are roadmapping for, made out of a subset of the total of teams in the organisation). We know how those different things relate to each other in terms of dependencies. And we roughly know who is best placed to own each of the work streams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The are two missing pieces still.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;strategy&#34;&gt;Strategy&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ideally you should write your strategy briefs first. We had some drafts, but we made a conscious decision to invert the order. Our aim was to gain clarity about the future and prepare ourselves for the imminent OKR planning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have already written a formal strategy, for the most part, your projects will come directly from it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;okrs&#34;&gt;OKRs&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Company-driven goals might clash somehow with your roadmap. You wouldn&#39;t know until close to the beginning of next quarter, when company OKRs are refreshed (this might be different in your case, depending on the cadence of your organisation).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though adjustments might be necessary, company OKRs don&#39;t invalidate your roadmap, but you might want to reserve certain capacity to make sure you can accommodate unexpected needs. Typically this will be in the form of OKRs that require enabling others to deliver their goals, or to contribute to pushing metrics in reaction to a market change (like during COVID).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having a roadmap will prepare you better with the tools you need to accomplish company OKRs. It&#39;ll be much easier to find something in your roadmap that supports one of those company goals, than having to come up with an entirely new project on the spot. So you are increasing the chances of having something ready, that is aligned with both the company goals and your long term vision for your area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;7-share-with-the-teams-and-keep-iterating&#34;&gt;7. Share with the teams and keep iterating&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s important to get buy-in from the team that will actually work on the projects. You want to give everyone a chance to contribute and provide input if they have anything to add. Share your roadmap, ask for feedback, learn and iterate. Do that a few times and you will have a solid and always up-to-date roadmap, ready for any planning cycle.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Developing Your Critical Thinking</title>
      <link>https://retrolog.io/blog/developing-your-critical-thinking/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Aug 2018 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://retrolog.io/blog/developing-your-critical-thinking/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://retrolog.io/images/developing-your-critical-thinking.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every day we need to make decisions as leaders. But this is often not easy. How can we improve our chances to make good decisions? There are many techniques for this, one of which is critical thinking. This technique is particularly effective, and it allows us to deconstruct the situation removing undesired bias and revealing hidden issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you use critical thinking, rather than making a decision just because it feels right, you will scrutinise every available option and apply scepticism. Using the tools described below you will eliminate everything but the most useful and reliable information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is one way of approaching critical thinking based on 5 steps, as created by &lt;em&gt;Samantha Agoos&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Formulate the question appropriately&lt;/strong&gt;: find out what you are really looking for. This is not always straightforward, as the real enquiry can be obscured by other factors. If the underlying question is not clear, you can try the &lt;em&gt;5 whys technique&lt;/em&gt; to identify the root of the problem at hand (ask why 5 times in a row to explore reasons deeper than the obvious and immediate ones).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gather information&lt;/strong&gt;: having a clear idea of your question will help you determine what is relevant. You might ask an expert for their advise or seek other people&#39;s testimonies. This will help you weigh different options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Apply the information&lt;/strong&gt;: consider what concepts apply, be aware of what assumptions you are making and ask yourself if your interpretation of the situation is logically sound. By asking critical questions to yourself, challenging what you know about the problem, you will narrow down your alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consider the implications&lt;/strong&gt;: evaluate the consequences of choosing each option. Frequently, we tend to see only the short-term implications of our decisions, but it is important to consider the long-term impact as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explore other points of view&lt;/strong&gt;: think about why other people prefer an alternative that is different from your preferred one at this point. Even if you disagree completely, this will help you understand why the rest of the options might appeal to others. This way you will explore alternatives, reconsider your own choices and ultimately make more informed decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is just one technique, and it will not remove the difficulty of making a decision. But it can help you increase the number of positive choices you make. Critical thinking can definitely help you navigate through a sea of alternatives and find what you are looking for.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Improving Your Conversational Skills</title>
      <link>https://retrolog.io/blog/improving-your-conversational-skills/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Aug 2018 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://retrolog.io/blog/improving-your-conversational-skills/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://retrolog.io/images/improving-your-conversational-skills.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At work, great communicators have an advantage. They know how to have great conversations. Personality helps, but this is a skill that anyone can learn. Here I explore a few tips to improve your conversational skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Talk slowly: if you are like me, you will tend to speak faster than you should, particularly when you have a lot to say. Typically, good talkers do not rush into a conversation. Take your time to think. You will be perceived as calmer and more centred. And you will help the other person &amp;ldquo;pace&amp;rdquo; their dialog too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Focus on the conversation at hand: do not multitask! You will hear the message more clearly when you focus only on the conversation. This shows respect, and when you give them undivided attention, they will respect you more as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do not bring up controversial topics: there is a time and place for everything, but in general, your workplace is not good for controversy. Religion and politics are the most common ones. Even if you have strong views on particular issues, your goal is to respect everyone&#39;s different points of view. This kind of topics are best discussed with friends outside work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pay attention to nonverbal communication: for example, eye contact shows respect, nodding shows comprehension, facing them directly shows attention and focus, and leaning in demonstrates interest. Even when you are not speaking, your body language says a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make the other person feel comfortable and confident: use positive questions to show interest and allow them to share their thoughts and expertise. Give them the opportunity to feel like an expert and explain what they have in mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay positive even when you disagree: you could choose not to respond to their comment, but as a minimum be respectful. If someone is moaning about someone else in front of you, you might say that you are not sure you see the issue the same way, and focus on how to move forward. That way, even if you do not agree, you were not offensive to them either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope this tips will help you take your conversation skills to the next level.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Providing Purpose</title>
      <link>https://retrolog.io/blog/providing-purpose/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jul 2018 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://retrolog.io/blog/providing-purpose/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://retrolog.io/images/providing-purpose.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A job pays the bills. But if that is all it means to you, it will be hard to feel inspired. It is not unreasonable to expect a job to excite you and provide you with a higher sense of purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Purpose is feeling that your time is being well spent and your work is adding value to something that matters. For some people it is easier to feel purpose, and also some vocations are simply more likely to help you feel purpose e.g. teachers and healthcare professionals are frequently included in this category.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But most people are not wired to feel purpose that easily and most jobs are not clearly fulfilling in that sense. You, as a manager, have to effectively lead those people. What can you do?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can indeed create a sense of purpose. In order to do that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, you will need to articulate the important goals they are serving beyond their daily work. This could be related to the community, or education, or environmental goals. It is too easy to get lost in the routine and miss the bigger picture your organisation serves. As a manager, your duty is to remind them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, you must find ways to link your employees to the outcomes of their work, e.g. if they create applications for students, show them feedback from real users. Or even better, invite some to the office so that they can share their experiences first hand. Anything that can help them feel the value they are adding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, give your team voice and autonomy. That is input in the decision-making process and freedom to be creative and not micromanaged. This will have the side benefit of improving trust and creating opportunities for development. But will also make people feel they are in control of their own time, making a genuine and invaluable contribution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For some jobs it might be easier, but for any job, with a little effort, you can help people get over their routine and feel purpose.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building Self-Awareness as a Manager</title>
      <link>https://retrolog.io/blog/building-self-awareness-as-a-manager/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jun 2018 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://retrolog.io/blog/building-self-awareness-as-a-manager/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://retrolog.io/images/building-self-awareness-as-a-manager.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For most people, it is hard to objectively self-evaluate their work and behaviours. Great leaders learn to build strong self-awareness. There are two main sources of information that can help you with this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;personal-data&#34;&gt;Personal Data&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal is to learn about yourself, focusing on your strengths and weaknesses. You can achieve this by keeping track of your performance over time. There are three sources of data you can use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look for a trend line that describes the evolution of your average performance in a period of time, maybe 6 or 12 months.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look also for your relative performance compared to other members of the team.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally, go back to your previous performance evaluations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;feedback-from-others&#34;&gt;Feedback from others&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this case the goal is to find at least one or two people that are willing to give you feedback. You will need someone more experienced than you for this, that has good exposure to your work, behaviours and performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you know who they are, approach them in private and ask them from their perspective on you and your work. Try to be as respectful as possible, they are investing time and effort in giving you quality feedback after all. The golden rule is, make sure you let them talk!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;putting-things-together&#34;&gt;Putting things together&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is important to self-reflect on the data we can gather ourselves before asking others for their opinions. This way we will be more open to receiving feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do this two or three times per year and you will have developed a deeper self-awareness that will help you improve faster at work.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>